there's so much to talk about in
technology now the title is debating
technology I don't think there's a
debate technology yes or no um but in
covering Silicon Valley for 25 years I
often hear you know technology can be
used for good or bad which is inherently
true but sometimes that's used to say
especially by the makers of the
technology well it's going to be used
for good or bad hopefully the good
outweighs the bad and to me that
neglects our responsibility to push and
steer and limit the tech techology so it
is used for good um but we're going to
talk about this is a moment of great
excitement especially with artificial
intelligence Robotics and all these
Technologies um but it's also a moment
of great concern a lot of people have
legitimate fears about what this change
will bring uh that's enough from me I'm
excited to be joined by David Newman
head of the MIT media lab and Yan Lon
who leads AI uh research and other
activities at meta um Dava maybe to
start with you I mean you have such a
broad background in technology from
obviously your experience in space where
is your head these days what are the
problems uh and areas that you think
need our attention and where are you
wrestling your brain around thank you
everyone good morning pleasure to to be
with
you so where's my brain typically an
outer space you know thinking about
becoming an uh you know uh inter species
will we find life elsewhere it's not
option b so where my head really is and
thinking about technology and the
disruption
that we feel and that much more orders
of magnitude more disruption that's
coming so maybe I paint the picture it
really is I think a a you know
technology super cycle now convergence
of probably three Technologies at once
you know the Industrial Revolution that
was it was okay when we put one
technology at a time geni took me 30
seconds before getting into this AI it's
it's coming large langu it's but it
still it's an infancy at the MIT media
lab we've been working on AI for 50
years so now that it's uh common in
everyone's hands a co-pilot I'm sure
we're going to debate that and talk a
lot about it with my esteemed colleague
and and expert developing that we're
doing a lot most important thing I want
to emphasize just in the introductory
about Ai and gen AIS we design for
humans human centered human flourishing
at the media lab so is it trusted is it
responsible that's that's the premise
actually we don't do it if it's not but
hold on to your seats you know everyone
um rocket launch is coming soon soon I
think we'll all be talking about gen bio
if you're not already not just synthetic
bio but generative bio we don't bio
biology is is is organic so when AI
morphs into to gen bio it's no longer a
large language model but we're working
on actually media lab um you know large
nature models now you're ingesting
biology and genetics and biological wrap
that all around into sensors internet of
things we're pretty famous for I call it
now internet of all things because I
have iot for the oceans to monitor all
biodiversity for the land climate air
atmosphere you might think of and from
space more than half of all of our
climate variables are now measured from
space so that so hopefully that kind of
technological Whirlwind I don't know
what else to call it you know coming
with geni Gen bio sensors measuring
everything to finish up I put humans and
human centered design right in the
middle and asking The Upfront questions
is it intentional for human flourishing
and all living things flourishing if the
answer to that is no with our algorithms
then I don't think we should be doing it
and Yan that's a that's a good point to
turn to you how do we make sure uh the
AI we can build is the AI we want how
are you trying to focus your work and
the development at meta to make sure
that we get an AI that works for
Humanity
um there's two two answers to this the
first thing is you try to make it work
well and
reliably uh and uh the the the flavor of
generative AI or AI that we have at the
moment um is not quite where we want it
to be in terms of is very useful we we
should push it we're pushing it um
trying to make it more reliable trying
to um um make it applicable to kind of a
wide area of a wide range of of of areas
um but it's not where we want it to be
and it's not very controllable um for
various reasons so I think what's going
to happen is that um within the next
three to five years we're going to see
the emergence of a new brand or Paradigm
for for AI uh architectures if you want
um which um may not have the the the
limitations of current AI systems um so
what are limitations of current systems
there are four things that are essential
to inell behavior that they really don't
do very well one is understanding the
physical world second one is having
persistent memory and third and fourth
are being capable of uh reasoning and
complex planning and llms really are not
capable of any of this um there is a
little bit of an attempt to kind of Bolt
some wordss on them to kind of get them
to do a little bit of this but uh but
ultimately this will have to be done in
a different manner um so there's going
to be a another revolution of AI over
the next few years and we may have to
change the name of it because it's
probably not going to be generative in
the sense that we understand it today um
so that's that's a first point some
people have called this in different uh
uh names um so technology we have today
um large language models deals very well
with the discrete world and language is
discret
um I don't want to upset stepen who is
St Pinker is in the room here but to
some some extent language is
simple
U uh much simpler than understanding the
real world which is why we have ai
systems that uh can pass the bar exam or
solve equations and things like that do
pretty amazing things uh but we don't
have robots that can do what a cat can
do um the understanding of the physical
world of a cat is way Superior to
everything we can do with with with AI
um so that tells you the physical world
is just way more complicated than than
human language um and it's because why
is language simple it's because it's
discrete objects and the same with DNA
and proteins right is discrete so so the
application of those generative methods
to this kind of data has been incredibly
successful because it's easy to make
predictions in a discrete world you can
never predict what word will come after
a particular text but you can produce a
probability distribution of all possible
words in the dictionary and is only a
finite number of them if you want to
apply the same principle to
understanding the physical world you
will have to train a system to predict
videos for example right show a video to
the system and ask it to predict what's
going to happen next and that turns out
to be a completely intractable task um
so the the techniques that are used for
large language models do not apply to uh
video prediction uh so we have to use
new techniques which is what we're
working on at at at MAA but it may take
a few years before that that pens out um
so that's kind of the
um the first thing and and what that
pans out um it will open the door to
brand new class of of applications of AI
because we'll have systems that we'll be
able to uh reason and plan uh because
they they will have some mental model of
the world that current system we don't
have so they'll be able to predict the
consequences of their actions and then
plan a sequence of actions to arrive at
a particular
objective um and that may open the door
to U real agentic system is talking
agent Ki but nobody knows how to do it
and that's kind of one way to do it
properly and also to
robotics um so the coming decade may be
the decade of Robotics because that was
the first answer and the second answer
which is shorter um the way to make sure
that AI is uh applied properly is
to give the tools for people to build
diverse set of AI systems and assistants
um with which understand all the
languages in the world uh all the
cultures uh value systems Etc and that
can only be done through open source
platforms so um I'm I'm a big believer
in the idea that uh the way the AI
industry and and and ecosystem is
going um open source Foundation models
are are going to be dominant over
proprietary systems and they they're
going to basically be the substrate for
the entire industry they already are to
some extent uh and and they're going to
enable a really wide diversity of uh of
AI systems and I think it's crucially
important because within a few years you
and I both are wearing those smart
glasses right and you can talk to an ni
assistant
uh using those things and ask any
question but pretty soon uh we're going
to have more and more of those things
with displays in them and everything and
all of our digital diet would be
mediated by AI
assistance and so if we only have access
to three or four of those assistance
coming from you know a couple companies
on the west coast of the US or China is
not going to be good for cultural
diversity
democracy uh everything else you know we
need a very wide diversity of AI
assistance that can only happen with
open source which is what meta is um
being promoting as well well thank you
both I think that sets up up well for a
discussion and as a reminder this is a
town hall not a panel so we're going to
be bringing in both the audience here in
this room of incredible guests as well
as uh those on the live stream so the
first thing we did is we asked uh the
folks on the live stream uh there is a
slido you can join um also we asked how
would you like these emerging
Technologies uh to contribute to the
Future and we're not going to show all
the answers but here's a word cloud of
some of what uh folks have said so if we
just quick quickly look at
that well that's the question I'm not
quite sure how we get to the answer new
technology it's a blank slate all right
well I'm sure people you know talked a
lot about both what they're excited
about and what they're worried about um
you know I want you to get ready with
your questions in the room I'm sure
everyone has some but Yan I want to
follow up on the open source thing
because there's really a big debate I
mean as I said technology is not a
debate but the approaches we take and
certainly open source has all the
advantages that you mentioned um it
allows people all over the world to join
in only a few people are going to be
able to train one of these giant uh
models but a lot of people can make use
of them and can contribute at the same
time there's a real concern that taking
this powerful technology and giving it
to the world and saying basically meta
says here's our acceptable use policy
here's what you and can't do but to be
honest there's really no way of
enforcing that once it's out it's out
how do we make sure something is both
open source and
safe uh so what what we do at meta is
that when we distribute a model so by
the way we say open source but we know
technically those things are not really
open source because you know the code
the source code is available the weights
of the model are available for free and
you can use them for whatever you want
except with those restriction Clauses uh
you know don't use it for for for
dangerous things um so the the the way
we do this is that uh we we fune those
system um and Red Team them to to make
sure that at least to first order uh
they're not you know kind of spewing
complete nonsense and or or or toxic
cancers or or things like that but um
but there is a there's a limit to how
well that works and and those those
systems can be J broken you can uh do
what's called prompt injection so type
of prompt that will basically
take the system outside of the domain
where it's been fine-tuned and you know
you're going to get to its uh you know
uh kind of root uh uh things and then
that depends on uh what training data is
been pre-trained on uh which of course
is a combination of high quality data
and not so high quality data and Dava is
putting something like that into the
world I mean obviously there are
benefits to open sourcing that way MIT
is Pioneer in open source there's an MIT
license for open source I can't remember
it may even be the license that meta
uses um at the same time when you talk
about having this technology be human-
centered and putting humans and our
needs and concerns at the Forefront what
do you think needs to be done you talked
about synthetic biology and you know all
these things obviously there's a lot you
know there's a lot of neglected diseases
there's a lot of things we want to use
these new technologies for and we don't
want everyone just in their home
developing new microorganisms to run
around so what are your thoughts on how
we make this technology broadly
available but still safe yeah thanks
that's that's the question and seeing
what people are concerned about too AI
in space I agree with that we can talk
about the word cloud but so um you based
on open source platforms with but with
guardrails and and we have to be all
held accountable right now we can you
know ask the the audience as well you
know does AI work for you what I mean do
you trust it is it responsible is it
representative of you do you think it
has the training data that represents
you well let's ask the audience how many
of you feel that you think it's safe
secure and um you know you're going to
launch in and use it today you know
during this
debate anyone raise their hand well I I
think there's the answer and I think
it's not how many people would be open
to AI would love to use AI once they do
feel it's safe and secure
everyone so that's why I asked the
question so it's not there yet so it
does it's not representative doesn't
represent everyone in this room um the
world is much more diverse than what we
have in in the room so it doesn't work
so maybe this is where the debate starts
so we're you know open source we want to
be open source want all the you know all
my students are superstars and Geniuses
want all the next generation of the
world to be able to give their
creativity their curiosity because
that's how human flourishing happens but
if we just let the algorithms uh again
on their own I think that we really have
to rethink is it is it where's the
trading data come from where's the
transparency where is the transparency
does it work for all of us I think if uh
those an those questions are answered
well we have a we' have the majority of
folks you know opting in and then and
hopefully making it better right open
sourcing is because you can get all the
good ideas and enhance things so we see
that you know coming enhancing it making
it work for everyone but I think we you
know here and in very intentional
where's the transparency where's the the
trust uh you know has it kind of gotten
away from us so these are really
important questions and Yan I want to
push you one more time and then I really
I hope you all have your questions ready
because I'm coming to you next um I want
to push you one more area which is
values and I wrote about this last year
that you know social media has been
about content moderation what speech do
you allow where do you draw the lines
obviously you know it's something that
meta has spent a lot of time on has had
different approaches um but it strikes
me that these AI systems are going to
have to have values and I wrote that you
know your PC doesn't really have a set
of values your smartphone you know yes
there's some App Store moderations so
you know at the extreme there's some
limits um but the AI system is going to
answer the hard questions and you know
how do we do that in a world where you
know people in the Middle East have
different values than uh people in the
US people in the US have different
values than people in the US um recently
meta made ACH bunch of changes to how
it's going to approach that allowing a
lot more speech even uh that might be
considered very offensive distasteful
even
dehumanizing where is the role of the
tech companies in putting their thumb on
the scale of the values you know I how
much pressure is there going to be from
governments to control what speech how
AI chat Bots for example answer
questions around gender sexuality human
rights so there is a interesting debate
about this so this is not specialy I
should tell you but um but it's an
interesting topic nevertheless that I'm
interested in um
So Meta has gone through several phases
uh concerning content moderation and uh
how how is how best to do it um and uh
including with questions not not just
about toxic content but also about uh
disinformation which is much more
difficult problem to deal with so uh
until 2017 let's say uh detecting things
like hate speech on U on social networks
was very difficult because the
technology just wasn't up to Snuff and
counting on users to flag uh
objectionable content and then have it
reviewed by humans just doesn't scale
particularly if you need those humans to
speak every language in the world um and
so that just was not technologically
possible you just couldn't do it
uh and then what's happened is that
there's been this you know enormous
progress in natural language
understanding uh since 2017 basically
and and that has made enormous amount of
progress so now detecting H speech in
every language in the world is basically
possible with some good level of of
reliability so the proportion of ha
speech for example that is taken down
automatically by AI system was on the
order of 20 to 25% late 207 uh late 2022
5 years later because of Transformers
are supervision you know all the stuff
that that uh uh is everybody is excited
about today uh it was
96% now that probably went too far
because uh the number of false positives
of of of good content that was taken
down is probably pretty high so there
are countries where people just want to
kill each other and you probably want to
kind of you know calm down so so put the
threshold detection threshold pretty low
countries where there is an election and
and you know things going to r r up so
also you want to lower the threshold
detection so that more things get U get
taken down to sort of Camp people down
um but then most of the time you want
people to be able to debate important uh
societal question including for
questions that are you know very
controversial like like gender and and
and political opinions some somewhat
extremes and so what's um what's
happened recently is uh the company
realized it went a little too far and
and there were like just too many Force
positives um and now the the the
detection trols are going to be changed
a little bit to
authorize uh discussions about topics
that are you know big questions of
society even if if the topic is
offensive to some to some people so
that's that's a big change um but it's
it doesn't mean content moderation is
going to go away it's just there it's
just you change the threshold and again
the answer is different in different
countries so uh in Europe it's illegal
hate speech is illegal um you know
neonazi propaganda is illegal right you
you have to do it for legal reason you
have to moderate that for legal Reason
Not So in in the US in various countries
you have different standards as as you
said um then there is a question of
disinformation and there uh until um
until now meta used uh fact checking
organization to fact check the big uh
post that had a lot of uh gathered a lot
of attention but it turns out this
system doesn't work very well it doesn't
scale you don't have a large coverage of
uh of the content that is being posted
because those organization you know
there's only a few of them and they have
a few people working for them and and so
they they can't just uh debunk every you
know uh dangerous misinformation that
circulates on social networks so the
system that is being implemented now
that will be red out is um is qu forcing
essentially have people themselves um um
you know kind of write uh comments uh on
on uh on posts that are controversial um
and that is likely to have much better
coverage there are some studies that
show that this is a a better a better
way of doing conent moderation
particularly if you have some sort of
karma system where people who make
comments that turn out to be reliable or
liked by other people then so that they
get promoted several uh uh forums have
used this system in for many years um so
the The Hope um with the MAA is that
this will actually work better and it
also has a big Advantage which is that U
meta has never seen itself as having the
legitimacy to decide what is right or
wrong for society um and so in the past
has asked governments to to
regulate as governments around the world
this was during the first Trump
Administration uh tell us what is
acceptable on social networks on on on
for online discussion and the answer was
cricket there was basically no answer I
think there was some discussion with the
government in France but uh the Trump
administration at the time the first one
said where the First Amendment here go
away you're on your own um so the all
those those policies kind of resulted
from this absence of uh regulatory
environment um and now it's quite source
is you know content moderation for the
People by the people well there's much
more uh we could talk about but I don't
want to oh yes if I could get us back to
values I think that's that's the right
question so um if we can that's that
should be the first question uh what are
the values so and you have to be able to
articulate your values like articulate
my values it's it's up to leadership to
articulate values so you know for me is
um Integrity Excellence curiosity
community community encompasses
belonging and collaboration so if you
can articulate your values and then as
designers as Builders as technologists
flow from those values we could get it
right what if we get this right so I
think you really we need to back up so
Med I should articulate and in the you
know the checking what are the values do
we have aligned values then we can
collaborate then we can all collaborate
work together and respect um our
cultural differences and all the you
know the Cornucopia that humanity is and
and that's that's wonderful and that's
the opportuni is to go across uh you
know all the cultures but but I think we
fundamentally still have to have the
discussion about values and do we share
values that's that's the I think
fundamental yeah the core core core
share values that you know need to be
expressed I mean the in that sense the
content policy from it are published
right so it's not it's not a secret um
but then there is the implementation of
it right and and and um M the p as made
mistake deploy the system and then
realize that this is not working the way
we wanted it so can of R it back and
replace it by other systems it's it's
constantly but you could lead you could
you could lead in industry and you know
lean in and be out in the front that
discussion uh by all measure actually ma
is is leading in terms of content
moderation absolutely and daa is that
your sense I mean are you concerned with
the new policies that um you know I mean
obviously it's very difficult to say
what are shared values there are a lot
of debates again even in the US at the
same time um you know we talked about a
human centered world and the new
policies um certainly allow a lot of uh
dehumanizing Speech whether it's uh
comparing women to objects uh trans
people to it g people mentally ill have
they gotten that balance right or are
they going no we don't have the right
policies absolutely no emphatically
no we know what's wrong and
right we know human behavior we know
civility we know what makes you happy
when you're teaching your kids we should
probably look at at our our children our
kids and the Young Generation as as well
especially when we talk about um values
and and what we have and and you know
who who we who we aspire to to be
there's a chance to get it right but um
you know we've run the experiment uh you
know internet one internet two I think
we've running the experiment so this is
the opportunity to to get it right I
want to bring in the audience who who
would like to uh build on the discussion
we've had and please just say your name
and where you're from uh there's a mic
coming around but keep the intro short
and ask a question I'm Mukesh from
Bangalore India uh so yeah your group is
at the Forefront of AI research and so
are many other groups around the the
world do we know where we are going like
can is there a mental model for 5 years
from now because we all speculating and
asking questions about where a is today
challenges and so on do we understand
where we're going enough to we have some
prediction about 5 years or is just too
much wide open so my colleagues and I
ADM certainly understand where we are
going I can't claim to understand what
other people are are doing particularly
the ones that are not publishing their
their research and basically you know
have clammed up in in recent times um
but um the way I see things going so
first of all uh I think the the shelf
life of the current Paradigm uh large
language model is fairly short probably
3 to five years I think within five
years nobody in the right mind would use
them anymore at least not as kind of the
central component of an AI system um one
analogy that some people have made which
have uh recycled is um llms are are good
at manipulating language but not at
thinking okay manipulating language is
done by little piece of the brand right
here called the bar area it's about it's
about this big it only popped up in the
last few hundred thousand years can't be
that
complicated what about this the frontal
cortex that's where we think right we we
don't know how to reproduce this um so
that's what we're working on um you know
having systems s of build Mentor models
of the world
so if the plan that we're working on
succeeds you know with the the the
timetable that that we we uh we hope uh
within 3 to 5 years we'll have system
that are complete different Paradigm
they may have some level of Common Sense
they may be able to learn how the world
works from observing uh the world go by
and maybe interacting with it uh you
know deal with uh real world not just
discret discret World um and open the
door to another application I want to
give you just a very U uh interesting um
calculation uh a typical uh fish model
today large language model is train on
20 trillion tokens or 30 trillion tokens
uh a token is typically three bytes so
that's about uh you know 9 10 to the 13
bytes 10 to the 14 bytes okay let's
round it up uh this basically is uh
almost all of publicly available text on
the internet it would take any of us
sever hundred, years to read through it
okay um now compare this with what a
four-year-old has seen in the four years
of life uh you can put a number on how
much information gets to the visual
cortext or or or through touch if you BL
um and it's about um it's about 2 2
megabytes per second about 1 Megabyte
per optic nerve about 1 B per second per
optic nerve fiber we have one million of
them for each eye uh multiply this by
four years and now four in four years um
a child has been awake a total of 16,000
hours so figure out how how many bites
that is 10 to the 14 same number in four
years um so what it tells you is that
we're never going to get to human level
AI
which some people call AI but that's a
misn um we're never going to get to
human level AI by just training on text
we need systems to be able to learn how
the world works from sensory data um and
and so that means LNS are not it talk
about that not we're not going to get
hum within two years like what some of
people have been saying and you've been
talking about that as well yeah so
that's that's my point you know this is
and it's infancy so I think it's
actually you know um that's the way to
clear it where you know LMS are in the
infancy is you know infant I
four-year-old is not infant but very
very early on uh but when you move to
generative biology um training data when
you move to sensors internet of thing
when you move to you know the almost
infinite you know amount of of data
information we have and um you know just
multi- sensory you're talking about you
know you have the the glasses on you
know your vision but you're looking at
text how much do we get tacti hearing
sensing smelling right have you all had
your coffee this morning you know what's
the first thing what was the first thing
that you know you really related to this
morning probably you know breakfast
sense of coffee smell so would put the
multisensory capabilities again for for
humans and I want to be clear from the
earlier you know com Humanity
flourishing humanity and all living and
all living beings all all living the
appreciation for all of life for all of
life human centered design in terms of
some our Technologies but uh you you get
to choose your orientation you get to
choose who you're uh designing for and
so I think that's really important too
not the egocentric Humanity versus the
rest of you know it's it's that's that's
the question you know how long will we
be here um spaceship Earth Technologies
for space up there that's my that's my
specialty um it doesn't need us you know
so a little humility please being being
humble earth going to be fine without
Humanity we're a bit of a nuisance a
huge nuisance so you know Earth is 4.5
billion years old I have my sister
planet Mars probably find past life
there about 300 3.5 billion or so so
again that that view let's please you
know with with humility and approach
this and then the question is you know
do we want to live in Balance do we we
want to live the best lives we can and
flourish and then then I think you just
approach it you know with different
questions you approach solutions from a
from a different perspective thanks I
think I heard something over here I'm
not sure if it was a phone or a question
but I know I see a
hand um talk a lot about existence and
um there's a coming because we have a
live stream audience and say who you are
moris band light speed um for Dava um
you know you talk about AI you talk
about existence to I'm glad you're
making life or working on making life
human life a multiplanetary species um
where does AI fit in into this broader
need um do you see it as an existential
threat do you see it as an existence
enhancing technology for example
generative bio is it our great filter
thank you for the the the question so um
you know I think we're the threat I
think the people are the threat you know
not my not my algorithms uh and for you
know the question when I'm I do think
about you know searching finding life
elsewhere in the universe it's a huge
help so when you say ai ai is not very
useful anymore it's almost just like
saying technology so then we can get now
we should say the the specifics you know
if we're talking um so when it comes to
to travel space for me humans are here
on Earth We're sending our probes and
our scientific instruments so it has a
lot to do with autonomy and autonomous
system and no the human having
information here but that that that Loop
of of information sensing and and
exploration but these are all autonomous
um robots and systems we are going to
send people and then we bring our own
supercomputers with us so that first
human Mission to Mars will be it'll
surpass our current 50 years of
exploring on Mars so that's the benefit
of of humans or you know human intellect
but so so it's a great question so it's
a mix up is a threat we use it to the
advantage of again capabilities
searching exploring and you can get in
my case searching for the evidence of
Bio signatures or or finding life
elsewhere so when you're focused you
know and you know your mission and again
be very transparent about how you're
using algorithms Ai and we always bring
in uh something that's you know very
much uh Missing in in most of the
development when we get down to more
foundational models specific um you know
personalized you know foundational
capability whether it's for health or
climate or exploration you got to bring
in the physics so there physics is more
if you just if you let things go just
mathematically statistically I mean look
at where we're at fantastic but I'm a
big believer and again I'm biomimic
trying to I'm trying to understand
nature I'm trying to understand living
systems always bringing in like
foundational physics with my math and
you know and you proceed along that that
course so while we continue the
discussion in here I also invite those
online we have a couple questions for
you what excites you about the
technology that we're talking about what
worries you and we have the opport to do
some more word cloud so if you're online
and using slido please share your
thoughts there and then we had a
question
there uh they're gonna bring a
microphone everyone if you can just wait
for a mic it'll help those online
Martina hirayama state Secretary for
Education research and Innovation
Switzerland uh my question uh goes to
you Dava so you talk about uh values
concerning AI so we have a divide
concerning access to AI or not what
influence will it have uh if uh we
consider that we do not share the same
values on Earth in all areas where we
live not even talking
about space what influence will this
have on divide yeah it's um so again I
think it's fundamental to so um you know
I give a list of five or six so my hope
is it um we can agree on uh t or three
of those two or you know just two or
three of those you probably won't be uh
the entire set but but I think we have
to look for agreement and shared values
and and then and then work together and
um if not then that's maybe the scenario
that plays out of of the threat division
destruction I don't want that path I
think we have an alternate path so I
think the hard work is People to People
sure policies regulation what do we
agree on what do we agree on how what
what future scenarios and their
scenarios it's very plur what future
scenarios do we agree on and if we can
agree on some of those if we can share
some of those those values and I I think
we can we could take a poll you know see
if we can get one amongst all this you
know diversity here so that's uh you
know it's a it's not an answer it's just
part of the discussion of what can we um
share and what do we what do we share
together and and make that the building
blocks to to get it right and and Yan
that is kind of the challenge of
building these systems for a globe again
where the world doesn't agree on a lot
um there's hopefully some basic things
we agree on though it seems like we
struggle even on those I know you've
talked about using Federated learning
and and to really make sure the world is
represented in these models but how do
we build for a world where there is so
much disagreement again when AI systems
aren't going to just moderate content
they're going to create an answer
content well I I think the answer to
this is diversity so if uh again if you
have two or three AI system that that
all come from the same location you're
not going to get diversity so the only
way to get diversity is having systems
that
are uh you know train on all the all the
languages and cultures and VAR systems
in the world uh and those are Foundation
models and then they can be fine-tuned
by a large uh diversity of of people who
can build assistance with different
ideas of what you know good value
systems are and and then people can
choose so it's the same idea is a
diverse press right you need a diversity
of opinion in the Press um to to at
least have the the basic ingredient of
democracy so it's you know it's the same
for it's going to be the same for AI
system you you need them to be diverse
so one way to do this I mean it's quite
possible that it's quite likely that it
it's going to be very difficult for a
single entity to train a financial model
on all the data all the cultural data in
the world and that may eventually have
to be done in sort of a Federated
fashion or or distributed fashion where
every regions in the world or every
interest group or whatever has their own
Data Center and their own data set and
they contribute to training a a big
Global model uh that may eventually
constitute the repository of all human
knowledge I saw a hand over here and if
you can wait for the mic thanks yeah
well we're passing the mic and I think
that's that's much more exciting uh to
me more the Federated toing it again
transparency because then it's it's it's
more customized it's more personalized
it's going after you know for the work
that it's it's again going after a
medicine or health or a speciic a
specific you know breast you know it can
be more specific and much more precise
so to me that's very
exciting hi my name is MTA josi and I'm
from London um I was listening to a
panel yesterday and they talked about a
concept that really startled me and I
went back and did a bit of research on
it and it's called alignment faking in
llms uh which is about how you know the
llm models are giving answers which are
which they are faking to align to
whatever is being asked to them or
whatever the general can say is probably
an experiment that has happened in the
last few months but it was really
startling and I just thought I'd get a
few thoughts from you on that okay um I
have a perhaps a slightly controversial
opinion about this which is that uh to
some extent llms are intrinsically
unsafe okay because they're not
controllable you don't really have any
direct way of controlling uh whether
what they say is you know certain
characteristics you know with respects
guard rails the only way you can do this
is by training them to do it but of
course that training can be undone by
you know going outside of the the the
domain where where they've been trained
um so to some extent they're inally
unsafe now that's not particularly
dangerous because they're not
particularly smart either right so they
they're useful um they they are in terms
of intelligence they are more like
intellig assistance in the sense that
you know if they produce a text you know
that a lot of it can be wrong in it and
you have to kind of go you know do a
pass on it and correct some of the
mistakes and like you know know what
you're doing it's a bit like you know
driving assistance for cars we don't
have completely autonomous consumer cars
but we have driving assistance and it
works really well so same thing uh but
we should forget about llms so this idea
that somehow we should extrapolate the
uh capability of llms and and realize oh
they can you know fake the intention
first they don't have any intentions and
and like you know simulate values they
don't have any values um and uh and you
know convince people to do horrible
things they don't have any notion of of
of what this is at all um and as I said
they're not going to be with us five
years from now we're going to have much
better system that are objective driven
where the output that those system will
produce will be by by reasoning and the
reasoning will U guarantee that whatever
output is produce satisfy certain guard
rails and the system will not those
system will not be able to be um it
wouldn't be possible to jailbreak to
jailbreak them by changing the promp
basically because that would be sort of
hardwired in the in the guard rails so
given what Yan just said daa you know
the Big Talk the big buzzword this year
is agents and giving more power to these
llms given what Yan just said about
their limitations and this is one of the
companies making it should we be worried
about giving more autonomy and agencies
to A system that has no values makes
mistakes yeah well and I don't think so
I agree with what y said you know that
LM said they're not smart they don't
have rationality they don't have an
intention I mean they're just they're
just lacking think of them as you know
math math and statistical you know
probabilities like that so all of the
probably what we much more care about
you know in humans is well judgment
that's you know the question is like
well this is seems very alerting because
it's you know fakes fake fakes of any
types are are alert right so um the
question what do we do about this
because you know agents so you know
agenic uh you know it is turning into
gentic so simple there's some simple uh
I don't know if there are solutions
there just simple ideas we can do right
um you know we have copyright things and
things like that what if it just you
know comes up every time we're using a
generative uh you know model why is why
isn't it watermarked why isn't you know
to why don't we know that uh you know
what's you know is this coming from a
human is this you know coming from an
algorithm just just you know just
visually just saying you know just
Watermark that you know it's generative
just some more information about what
you're looking at so the person the user
you know if this is being you know
served up to someone that they can take
it I want to do the flip side of this
argument too debate you know with myself
I mean you know published a paper on um
unlocking creativity you know again with
machine learning it's fantastic some
generative capability you have an idea
we have an idea so we just do some
simple brainstorming
and generate again to me I like actually
images uh you know the text because it
it maps to the human brain we're almost
perfect in terms of image mapping and
and looking at visuals so you say my
sentence what's that image and you know
Yan can have has and we look down and
we're going to have a really nice
discussion it's going to help us
actually be more creative more we can
have more discussion if it's kind of a
prompt for us you know that's where it's
a tool you know it really is then an
assistant it's helping us Converse and
have a discussion or or a debate I think
it should definitely be flagged we know
we have to know where it comes from we
have to know you know what the
ingredients are into the recipe so it's
hard to believe we only have a couple
minutes left and I want to give each of
you a chance to give us one thing we
haven't talked about what aren't we
talking about enough that we should be
talking about and maybe we'll be talking
about next year okay I'm going to go by
the list that we're see here exactly
this is what excites you the most about
technology okay brain computer interface
forget about that uh this is not
happening anytime soon at least not the
invasive type that neuralink is working
on the the non-invasive type so things
like you know electrogram bracelets that
m is working on yes that's happening
this year um and that's exciting
actually uh but but like drilling your
brain no um except for clinical purpose
uh gaming virtual world meta of course
has been sort of very active in this in
this space with metaverse say
exploration you are the expert uh it's
exciting as well um regulation uh that's
a very interesting topic um that
um uh I think people are in government
have have been brainwashed to some
extent into believing in the existential
risk story and has led to regulation
that are frankly
counterproductive because the effect
that they have is essentially make uh
open source the distribution of Open
Source AI engine essentially illegal and
in my opion that's way more dangerous
than um than all the other potential
dangers um consumer robotics as I said
maybe the coming decade will be the
decade of uh of of Robotics because
maybe we'll have ai systems that are
sufficiently smart to understand how the
real world works and in your previous
Cloud there was efficiency and and power
uh consumption uh efficiency there is
enormous motivation and uh uh incentive
for the industry to make AI infs more
efficient so you don't have to worry
about people not being motivated enough
to make AI systems efficient this is the
main cost of running an AI system is
power consumption so enormous amount of
work there uh but the technology is what
it is thanks DAV we have a minute left
yeah speed round I'll take I'll take uh
three of them um um I um politely uh
disree brain computer interfaces um no
we it's it's not it's not off it's
happening now um in terms of we have a
digital central nervous system so we're
are already having brain control over
especially in the the area of
breakthrough and Technologies for
replacement for Prosthetics so half
human half robotic new robotic legs you
know uh get rid of phantom phantom foot
because the brain is literally
controlling the robot so it's uh we're
to the the cyborg phase we're doing that
it's it's implanted people are walking
around um soon will'll hopefully be
paraplegics in the future maybe
quadriple so the brain is controlling uh
you know a digital uh Central
nervousness the brain is quite powerful
so it's the surgery so I'd love to talk
about that but but that's here that's a
that's not even the future that's that's
the now um after you know space we
talked about a little bit but again for
scientific purposes uh you know Finding
life what does that why explore out sour
because it tells us it's not option b
sorry Elon it's not option b it's for
flourishing humanity is to appreciate
all of us together our humanity and what
we can get right here on Earth and
definitely living in balance with Earth
so but it's necessary
because when we design for space in the
extreme environments of the Moon Mars
you name it Europa Clipper you anywhere
in the solar system exoplanets it's
because for us it pushes us it pushes
the technology makes me um you know
really sharp in the game and ser as
technology so very optimistic about that
I think we will find the evidence of
life or past life in the next decade
robotics this is um consumer robotics
okay um but what if we what if it's just
the robotic again it Hardware software
robotics should think of you know
physical systems well guess what now
what robots to they are the AI they're
the algorithm they're the software so we
do get to that physical cyber we get to
where we don't talk about hardware and
software we get to know just the
robotics or the machine it's it's
embedded with uh the software I my uses
my favorite um use cases and for health
you know revolutionizing um
individualized you know personalized
medicine things like that rather than
buying it and more stuff and more stuff
and more consuming what if you you make
your own again we're back to open source
let everyone you know do it yourself
make it yourself open source it and use
it from all recycled you know let's
think about you know what's circular so
what can we do with everything any waste
that's the new to me that's uh the new
robotic you know informed physical cyber
system of the future in the hands of
course of our our kids and they'll do
some just a little bit of Education
they'll do some pretty wonderful things
with it if you leave it to the next
Generation Well that's a great place uh
to leave things we are going to have to
leave it there thank you so much David
Newman from MIT Yan Lon from meta
everyone in the room and everyone who's
joined
us thank you